A Guide to the Rockefeller University records, Faculty-Student records, Sponsored Programs, Grant records FA1328
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University records, Faculty-Student records, Sponsored Programs, Grant records
1944-1977
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University.
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research.
FA1328
5.4 Cubic Feet 12 document boxes
Biographical / Historical
In March 1960 an Office of the Registrar was established to maintain records of faculty and students. This was a function which to this date had been handled by the Dean of Students and through the Office of the President. Earlier records of the scientific staff had been kept in the Office of the Business Manager. The first appointment to the position of Registrar was Marian Lucius who resigned in June 1972.
The functions of the office developed as it became an adjunct to the Office of the President. Reports to the New York State Education Department were made from this office. Various statistical data on institutional facilities, such as the library; the number of degrees granted; subjects and rank of instructional staff were filed through this office to be reported to the State Department of Education. When a program of state-aid to non-public institutions of higher education was established required reports were made each year.
After the resignation of Marian Lucius, Phyllis Viets was appointed and served to June 1974.
Antonia Siddiqi, from the Office of the President, took charge of the funtions of the Office of Faculty and Student records in addition to her work on the Grant Proposals and Grant Programs of the various laboratories. In 1979 Antonia Siddiqi became Secretary to the Board of Trustees as well as Director of the Office of Sponsored Programs with Eleanor Gibson handling much of the routine of Faculty and Student records.
Scope and Contents
Contains early grants, grants made for construction in new laboratory space or new health research facilties, as well as institutional grants made for trainee or post-doctural fellowships, and grants made to support research of a scientist(s).
Arrangement
Primarily arranged alphabetically by the name of the scientist receiving the grant, with early grants generally arranged in sequence.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of the RAC.
File Plan
Former Classification: I 370.2
- Grants, 1955-1958 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Summaries and listings of pending and unexpected grant balances. Includes correspondence with the Bursar and the Business Manager.
- Grants, 1957-1964 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  General correspondence between the Business Manager and D. W. Bronk and the National Science Foundation (NSF). Includes June 1964 statement from NSF clarifying possible conflicts of interest for NSF Board Members.
- Grants and Laboratory Development, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  NSF grants 1959-1960. Plans and proposals for completion of laboratory space in the South Laboratory. Correspondence is between F. Brink, Alan Waterman and Douglas Whitaker.
- Grants for Health Research Facilities, 1956-1958 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Correspondence dealing with applications for financial support for new Rockefeller Institute laboratories.
- Grants for Health Research Facilities, 1959-1962, 1968, 1970, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- NIH Post Doctoral Fellows, 1960-1965 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- NSF Graduate Traineeships, 1963-1968 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Agosta, William C., 1969 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Alfred P. Sloan Foundation
- American Cancer Society, 1946-1959 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  1946-1951 first granted to provide support to continue the work started in the laboratory of James Murphy. 1953-1955 grant continued to Rockefeller Institute under the direction of Keith R. Porter and Keffer Hartline. Includes 1959 correspondence with Douglas Whitaker.
- Archibald, Reginald M., 1959-1968 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  1959-1968 AM 03347 Study of post-menopausal osteoporosis. HE 07473 Angiotensin degradation in hypertension and edema 1962-1966.
- Archibald, Reginald M., 1958-1966 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  HEW, NIDR Training grant. 1963-1966 Biosynthesis and action of thyroxin AM 08216. 1958-1966 Enzymes of osseous and cartilagenous tissues AM 02772.
- Bearn, Alexander, 1959-1966 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  1959-1966 National Foundation grant.
- Chase, Merrill W., 1956-1968 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  1956-1968 Public Health Service
- Choppin, Parnell with Igor Tamm, 1967-1970 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  1967-1970 AT (30-1)-3983 Atomic Energy Commission Animal Virus Stucture and Development.
- Craig, Lyman C., 1958-1968 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  AM 02493-1081 Sturctural studies of active principles. Correlation of membrane diffusion and sedimentation data.
- Cranefield, Paul, 1967-1972 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  HL 11994 National Heart and Lung Institute "Effect of Drugs on cardiac arrhythmias".
- De Duve, Christian, 1962-1971 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  GB 5796. GB 588. 2871. 3621. B6-2333. NSF Biochemical studies on lysosomes and peroxesomes. GB26222 purchase of an electronic microscope.
- Di Cara, Leo V., 1969-1972 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  American Heart Association, PHS from NIMH.
- Dole, Vincent P., 1958-1968 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  AM 03963 Mobilization and transport of lipoids. AM 02427-0581 Metabolic activity of non-esterified fatty acids. A3963 The turnover of plasma lipoids in diabetic ketosis. 1964 NAPAN Narcotic Addiction.
- Dubos, Rene, 1960-1975 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  Health Research Council "Infection in Disease-Free and Germ-Free Animals".
- Dubos, Rene, 1964-1971 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  HEW "Intestinal Flora and Growth - Resitance to Disease". Includes 1959 and 1964 on "Latency and Reactivation of Bacterial Infections on which Dubos was co-investigator with Dr. Cynthia H. Pierce-Chase.
- Edelman, Gerald, 1960-1971 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  NIAMD and NSF. "Interaction and Energy Transfers in Biological Systems". 1966-1967 "Structure and Activity of Proteins".
- Franzl, Robert E., 1965-1972 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  RSF "Studies on the Induction of the Immune Response".
- Granick, Sam, 1960, 1964, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  NSF G14418. GB 270. GB 2617. GB 6818. "Studies toward growth and differentiation of chloroplasts in vitro." Growth and differentiation of plastids". "Control of heme and chlorophyll biosynthesis by certain steroids". 1966 grant request for Aharan Gibor withdrawn.
- Jackson, George, 1961-1971 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  Development Award-Research Career Program. "Helminth Nutrition; Excretion and Host Reaction".
- Jamieson, James D., 1966-1971 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  NIAMD AM 10928. National Cystic Fibrosis Research Foundation. "Cell Secretion and Membrane Formation in the Pancreas".
- Krause, Richard, 1968-1975 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  NIH Al-9267. Antibody Responses in Rabbits through Selective Breeding. 1967-1971 American Heart Association. "Innunochemical Studies on Streptococcal Antibodies".
- Kunkel, Henry G., 1957-1964 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  National Foundation.
- Leader, R. W., 1965-1971, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  Mink Farmers Research Foundation HEW Al 09046
- Lipmann, Fritz, 1961-1965 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  NSF G17436; PHS C3159. NSF 04341 1958-1961 "Metabolic Group Activation". "Biosynthetic mechanisms".
- Lloyd, David P. C., 1960-1971, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  NS 02816. National Institute of Neurological and communicative disorders and stroke. "Neuroglandular Physiology".
- Leob, Jacques (Box 3, Folder 11)
  Sponsored jointly bt RIMR and the Office of Naval Research, J. Ross Stevenson 1963-1964. Francis L. Lambert 1960-1961. Harold Hum 1959-1960. Includes correspondence between D. Whitaker, S. R. Galler, Office of Naval Research in establishment of program, reports and posters.
- Lundeen, Carl, 1971-1973 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  Corn products company.
- Lynch, Clara, 1957-1972 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  CA 08974 AI 07377. "A genetic study of sisceptibility of mice to experimental tuberculosis". Includes reprint from Laboratory Animal Care 19 (1969) 214-220 "The So-called Swiss Mice".
- McCarty, Maclyn, 1960-1971 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  1960-1967 "Training in Human Biology" basic research in biological sciences abd clinical investigation on abnormalities of human biology. Originally designed by Dr. F. Horsfall to be carried out in nine laboratories including McCarty, Dole, Dubos, Kunkel, etc. 1966-1971 Biomedical Science Support Grant. Includes correspondence with D. W. Bronk, F. Seitz, Wm. Stein, NIH and NIMH and listings of recipients.
- Marler, Peter R., 1966-1970 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  NSF "A comparative study of instinctive behavior in certain vertebrate animals". "A Comparative Study of Vocal Learning".
- Mauzerall, David, 1967-1970 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  Photobiological systems and their analouges
- Merrifield, Bruce R., 1956-1969 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  Original grant made to D. W. Woolley (principal investigator) who died in 1966. Merrifield continued work as "Synthesis of Peptides".
- Mirsky, Alfred E., 1956-1972 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  Physiological Activities of Nucleoproteins"
- Moody, Michael F., 1966-1972 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  Grant transferred to Brookhaven in 1972. "Fine structure of bacteriophages".
- Morse, Stephan I., 1964-1969 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  1962-1963 AI 04648 "Antigenic structure of staphylococci". "Lymphocyte response to B pertussis" Relinquished to Downstate Medical Center.
- Office of War Information, 1944-1946 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  Correspondence between H. S. Gasser and Cleveland Norcross regarding return of research materials and declassification for publication purposes.
- Pfaffman, Carl, 1965-1972 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  Department of the Navy N00014-66-C0067 "Physiological and behavioral mechanisms of taste and smell". 1965-1972 NSF GB 4198, GB 25001 "Physiological and behavioral mechanisms of the chemical senses. Primarily taste". 1968 NSF B80694C, GB7592 "Third International Symposium for olfaction and taste". 1969 Nutrition Foundation Grant "Metabolism, blood constitutants and taste sensitivity".
- Printz, Martin, 1971-1972 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  Transferred to University of California.
- Reich, Edward, 1964-1972 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Rizack, Martin A., 1961-1969 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  NSF
- Rothen, A., 1961-1970 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Sabatini, David, 1968-1972 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  Transferred to New York University School of Medicine.
- Siekevitz, Philip, 1963-1967 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  1967 NSF GB 6654 Equipment. 1963-1964 NSF GB 864 "Metabolism of different RNA species in sea-urchin embryos".
- Sunderlin, Charles E., 1971 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  NSF GP27971 1971 February-July. Site visits and consultation fees "Coordination of evaluation of interdisciplinary materials research laboratories."
- Tamm, Igor, 1961-1968 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  1961 U-1047 Health Research Council "Interaction of Human Viruses with receptors". NSF 1968 GB7681 with P. Choppin.
- Trager, William, 1962-1972 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  Biochemical changes accompanying malarial infection. "Biochemistry of intercellular parasitism in malaria".
- Voeller, Bruce, 1971-1972 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  NSF renewal of GB5350x, GB30611 "Developmental and evolutionary studies of pteridophyytes".
- Wang, Hao, 1961-1967 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  New York State Science and Technology Foundation
- Weiss, Paul A., 1955-1961 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  National Cancer Institute
- Weiss, Paul A., 1966-1975 (Box 5, Folder 13)
- William, Curtis A., 1957-1967 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  With Rene Dubos "Study on fractionation of tubercle bacilli related to basic fractionation of tubercle bacilli related to basic immunology and vaccination against tuberculosis". With Edward Tatum "Biochemical and cytological analysis of the cytoplasmic incompatibility reaction in Neurospora crassa".
- William, Curtis A., 1968-1971 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  1968-1969 "Effect of brain specifiic antibody on real behavior". Same title 1969-1971 National Association for Mental Health. 1965-1968 PHS AI 073456-01 "Regulation of plasma protein synthesis. 1970-1971 Grant Foundation: "Behavioral effects of antibody reaction in the brain".
- Wolf, Beverly, 1959 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  PF-74 American Cancer Society
- Zworykin, V. K., 1959-1962 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  PHS A3307 (c2). "Electronic Data Processing in Hematology".
- Zworykin, V. K., 1957-1959 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  Contract with Veterans Administration for clinical testing: "Pressure-sensitive ingestible radio capsule. 1961 proporal to NSF for printing photographs for paper: "Ultraviolet color-translating television microscopy".
- Immigration, 1928-1962 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  Correspondence by Waldo Flinn with U. S. Immigration and Naturalization authorities on behalf of and with students or scientists from abroad at Rockefeller Institute.
- Office of Scientific Research and Development, 1941-1944 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  Correspondence between H. S. Gasser, John D. Rockefeller, Jr, V. Bush, E. B. Smith, Irvin Stewart (Ex. Secr. OSRD) and others about contracts and grants during World War II and various provisions of contracts.
- Office of Scientific Research and Development, 1945-1947, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Visiting Investigators, 1955-1956 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Office of Naval Research, 1956 February-1959 April (Box 7, Folder 5)
  Correspondence on the establishment of the Jacques Loeb Associate in Marine Biology. The first recipient was Harold Humm.
- Public Health Service Fellowships, 1955 (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Public Health Service - Health Research Facilities, 1956-1959 (Box 7, Folder 7)
- NDEA Fellowships, 1959-1960 (Box 7, Folder 8)
- NSF Senior Foreign Policy Program, 1955-1972 (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Post-doctortal fellowships, 1960-1964 (Box 7, Folder 10)
- NSF Institutional Grants, 1960-1971 (Box 7, Folder 11)
- NSF Graduate Traineeships, 1964-1973 (Box 7, Folder 12)
- Foundation for Medical Technology, 1962-1966 (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Health Research Council, 1965-1970 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  Summary of grants received.
- NSF and NIH Fellowship Supplements, 1967 (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Clinical Research Volunteer Program, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Aherns, E. H., 1960-1973 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  NIH HE 06222 (1) - (13)
- Braun, Armin, 1956-1974 (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Choppin, Parnell - Atomic Energy Commission, 1970-1971 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  Animal Virus Structure and Development
- Becker, J. NIHAMD (with Edelman, G.), 1971-1972 (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Cohen, E. G. D., 1971-1973 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  NSF GP 30704 "Mathematical physics with special emphasis on statistical physics".
- Cunningham, Bruce, 1970-1973 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  Lectin Stucture and Cell Fractionation. "The Chemical structure of muscle proteins".
- Dobzhansky, T., 1965-1974 (Box 8, Folder 11-12)
- Dole, Vincent P., 1963-1975 (Box 9, Folder 1-5)
  Agreements with NY State Narcotics Control Commission. Health Research Council Grants 1963-1975. Agreements with NY City drug addiction 1971-1974.
- Ehrman, Lee, 1964-1974 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  Population fitness: genic and cytoplasmic determinants
- Estes, W., 1968-1973 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  Cognitive processes and mathematical psychology with Carl Pfaffman.
- Farquhar, Marilyn, 1968-1973 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  Research Career Grant GM25109-08. "Studies on Secretion in Anterior Pituitary Cells" started at University of California.
- Gillette, Peter NF Lincoln Fund, 1971-1974 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  Birth defects research program (sickle cell project).
- Gotschlich, Emil Health Research Council, 1971-1974 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  Immunochemical studies of gonococcal pili
- Hartline, H. K. USPHS NB00864, 1955-1969 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  Electrical activity, single receptors, neurons of eye
- Hotchkiss, Rolin and Magda PHS GM09427, 1962-1973 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  Biologically active polynucleatid structures
- Jackson, George PHS AI04842, 1967-1972 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  Helminth nutritian, excretion and host reaction
- Jamieson, James D., 1972-1973 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  National Cystic Fibrosis Research Foundation
- Kappas, Attallah NIH, 1969-1974 (Box 10, Folder 8-10)
  Reproductive hormones: biology and pharmacology. NIH 1971-1974 Lead poisoning pharmacological and clinical studies. Council for Tobacco Research 1971-1974.
- Kindt, Thomas Health Research Council, 1974-1977 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  Factors affecting resistance to streptococcal infection
- Krause, Richard PHS CC00473, 1969-1975 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  Genetic control of the immune response to streptococcal antigens
- Kreek, Mary Jeanne Health Research Council, 1974-1977 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  Narcotic drugs of use and abuse
- Kunkel, Henry G. NIAMDD AM10503, 1971-1973 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  Studies in Cystic Fibrosis
- Luck, David NSF, 1962-1974 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  Origin and development of mitrochondria in Neurospora Crassa, originally with George Palade.
- Miller, Neal NIH (Box 11, Folder 5)
- Morton, Herbert L. RR 00696-01, 1972-1973 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  Animal resources improvement program
- Nemethy, George NSF GB23920, 1970-1973 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  Noncovalent interactions in glycol solutions of micelles and of proteins.
- Pais, Abraham AEC, 1978-1972 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  AFOSR 69-1629 Theoretical high energy physics. Department of Air Force 1968-1970 The nature of fundamental reactions.
- Palade, George NIH, 1961-1973 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  National Lung and Heart Institute. Includes some NSF. "Localization of pore system in capillary walls". Scientist left to join Yale faculty.
- Pfaffman, Carl PHS, 1966-1973 (Box 11, Folder 10-12)
  Graduate training grants in behavioral sciences and psychobiology of behavior.
- Reeke, George AI 09921, 1970-1973 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  PHS "Structure of immunologically important molecules".
- Roberts, Richard, 1966-1969 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  Interactions between meningococci and phagocytic cells. James Hirsch listed as principal investigator.
- Sassa, Shigaru HRC, 1973-1976 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  Studies on lead poisoning, iron deficiency
- Shannon, James A. (Box 12, Folder 4)
- Siekevitz, Philip NSF, 1971-1973 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  Specialized research equipment
- Tatum, Edward L., 1957-1968 (Box 12, Folder 6)
- Tamm, Igor New York Heart Association, 1969-1970 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  Fellowship program.
- Tomasz, Alexander AEC, 1966-1971 (Box 12, Folder 8-10)
  30-1-3686. Cellular mechanisms involved in the uptake of DNA molecules during genetic transformation
- Weiss, Jay NIMH, 1971-1973 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  Psychological-neurological interactions in stress